<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine papers, which passed betwixt his Majestie of Great Britaine, in the time of his being with the Scottish army in New-Castle. And Mr. Alexander Henderson concerning the change of church government. Anno Dom. 1646.</title>
            <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01998</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52528750</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52528750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178715</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01998)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178715)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2768:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine papers, which passed betwixt his Majestie of Great Britaine, in the time of his being with the Scottish army in New-Castle. And Mr. Alexander Henderson concerning the change of church government. Anno Dom. 1646.</title>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>Henderson, Alexander, 1583?-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Broun, English booke-seller dwelling in the Achterom, at the signe of the English Printing House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Haghe :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D. C. XLIX [i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178715:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE PAPERS, which paſſed betwixt HIS MAIESTIE <hi>OF</hi> GREAT BRITAINE, In the time of his being with the SCOTTISH ARMY IN <hi>NEW-CASTLE.</hi> AND M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. ALEXANDER HENDERSON <hi>Concerning the change of</hi> CHVRCH GOVERNEMENT. Anno Dom. 1646.</p>
            <p>HAGHE Printed by <hi>Samuel Broun,</hi> Engliſh Booke-ſeller dwelling in the Achterom, at the ſigne of the Engliſh Printing Houſe, M. D. C. XLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178715:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178715:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Thought it not a miſſe to give thee this short account of the occaſion of the writing of theſe papers. When His Majeſtie was in the Scottish army, He was much preſſed to give way to the altering of the Governement of the Church of England from that by Bisshops under which it hath ſtood ever ſence it was a Church, to that by Preſbyteries.</p>
            <p>Before he could introduce ſo great a change he deſired that the lawfulnes, of both Governements might be freelie and freindly debated betwixt two of his Chaplains, and two others whom they should appoint.</p>
            <p>But this would not be granted Him,
<pb facs="tcp:178715:3"/>yet their importunitie ceaſed not, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore His Majeſtie, who proceeded not out of <hi>Paſſion</hi> but according to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> was forced him ſelfe alone, none of his Divines being ſuffered to come neare him, nor ſo much as an amanuenſis to help him to write, undertooke the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of Epiſcopacie before that of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Alexander Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, accounted one of the Prime, and moſt learned men amongſt them, and as ſuch, deputed by them to convince the Kings judgement, that ſuch an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration was not onlie lawful, but alſo neceſſarie.</p>
            <p>On whoſe ſide there is found moſt ſtrength of Reaſon I leave it to thy impartiall judgement, when thou haſt carefullie peruſed, and weighed theſe papers: which I heare preſent unto thee; from the true originall writen with His Majeſties own hand. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:178715:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>For M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Alex. Henderſon.</head>
            <head type="sub">His MAJESTIES firſt Paper.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Henderſon,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know very well what a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage it is for Me, to maintain an Argument in Divinity with ſo able and learned a man as your ſelf, it being your, not My pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; which really was the cauſe that made Me deſire to hear ſome learned men argue My Opinion with you, of whoſe abilities I might be confident, that I should not be led into an Errour, for want of having all, which could be ſaid, layed open unto Me: For indeed, My humour is ſuch, that I am ſtill partiall for that ſide, which I imagine ſuffers for the weakneſſe of thoſe that maintaine it; alwayes thinking that equall Champions would caſt the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance on the other part; Yet ſince that you (thinking that it will ſave time) deſire to goe another way, I shall not conteſt with you in it, but treating you as My Phyſitian, give you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178715:4"/>leave to take your own way of cure; onely I thought fit to warne you, leſt if you, (not I) should be miſtaken in this, you would be faine (in a manner) to begin anew.</p>
            <p>Then know that from My Infancy I was bleſt with the King My Fathers love, which, I thank God, was an unvaluable happineſſe to Me, all his dayes, and among all his cares for My education, his chief was, to ſettle Me right in Religion; in the true Knowledge of which, he made himſelf ſo eminent to all the World, that, I am ſure, none can call in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the brightneſſe of his Fame in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, without shewing their own ignorant, baſe Malice: He it was, who laid in Me the Grounds of Chriſtianity, which to this day I have been conſtant in; ſo that whether the worthineſſe of My Inſtructor be conſidered, or the, not few, years that I have been ſetled in My Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; it ought to be no ſtrange things, if it be found no eaſie work, to make me alter them: and the rather, that hitherto, I have (according to S.<hi>Pauls</hi> rule, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22.) been happy in <hi>not condemning my ſelf, in that thing which I allow:</hi> Thus having shewed you how, it remaines, to tell you what, I believe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to theſe preſent miſerable diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>No one thing made Me more reverence the Reformation of My Mother, the Church of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:178715:4"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> than that it was done (according to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> defence, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.18.) <hi>neither with multitude, nor with tumult,</hi> but legally and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly; and by thoſe, whom I conceive to have onely the reforming power; which with many other inducements, made Me alwayes confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the work was very perfect, as to Eſſentials; Of which number Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being undoubtedly one, I put no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but that would have been likewiſe alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if there had been cauſe; which opinion of mine, was ſoone turned into, more than, a confidence; when I perceived, that in this particular (as I muſt ſay of all the reſt) we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained nothing but according as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the Apoſtles to be the conſtant univerſall cuſtome of the Primitive Church; and that it was of ſuch conſequence, as by the alteration of it, we should deprive our ſelves of a lawfull Prieſthood, and then, how the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments can be duly Adminiſtred, is eaſie to judge: Theſe are the principall Reaſons, which make Me believe that Bishops are neceſſary for a Church, and, I think, ſufficient for Me (if I had no more) not to give My conſent for their expulſion out of <hi>England;</hi> but I have another obligation, that, to my particular, is a no leſſe tie of Conſcience; which is My <hi>Coronation Oath:</hi> Now if (as S.<hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.) <hi>he that doubteth is damned if he eate,</hi> what can I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178715:5"/>expect, if I should, not onely give way know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to My Peoples ſinning, but likewiſe be perjured My ſelf?</p>
            <p>Now conſider, ought I not to <hi>keep My ſelfe from preſumptuous ſinnes?</hi> and you know who ſayes, <hi>What doth it profit a man, though he should gaine the whole world, and looſe his owne Soul?</hi> Wherefore My conſtant maintenance of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (where there was never any other Government ſince Chriſtianity was in this Kingdome) Me thinkes, should be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commended than wondered at; My Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience directing me to maintaine the Lawes of the Land; Which being onely My endeavours at this time, I deſire to know of you, <hi>what warrant there is in the Word of God, for Subjects to endeavour to force their Kings Conſcience or to make him alter Lawes againſt his will?</hi> If this be not My preſent caſe, I shall be glad to be miſtaken; or, if My Judgement in Religion hath been miſled all this time, I shall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be better directed: till when, you muſt excuſe Me, to be conſtant to the Grounds which the <hi>King My Father</hi> taught Me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi>
                  <date>May 29. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:178715:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>For His MAJESTIE,</hi> Mr. Alexander Henderſon's firſt Paper.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">1. IT is your Majeſties royall goodneſſe, and not my merit, that hath made your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to conceive any opinion of my abilities; which (were they worthy of the ſmalleſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from your Majeſty) ought in all duty to be improved for your Majeſties ſatisfaction. And this I intended in my coming here at this time, by a free, yet modeſt expreſſion of the true motives &amp; inducements which drew my minde to the diſlike of Epiſcopal Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was bred in my younger yeares at the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity. Like as I did apprehend that it was not your Majeſties purpoſe to have the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion diſputed by Divines on both ſides; which I would never (to the wronging of the cauſe) have undertaken alone; and which ſeldome or never hath proved an effectuall way, for fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of truth, or moving the minds of Men to relinquish their former Tenents, <hi>Dum res tranſit à judicio in affectum;</hi> witneſſe the Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micks between the Papiſts and us, and among our ſelves, about the matter now in hand, theſe many yeares paſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sir,</hi> When I conſider your Majeſties edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation under the hands of ſuch a Father, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178715:6"/>length of time wherein your Majeſty hath been ſetled in your principles of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; the Arguments which have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in private and publique, eſpecially of late at Oxford, filled your Majeſties eares for the Divine right thereof; your Coronation Oath; and divers State-reaſons which your Majeſty doth not mention: I doe not wonder, nor thinke it any ſtrange thing that your Majeſty hath not at firſt given place to a contrary impreſſion. I remember that the famous <hi>Ioannes Picus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula</hi> proveth by irrefragable Reaſon (which no rationall man will contradict) That no man hath ſo much power over his owne underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as to make himſelfe believe what he will, or to thinke that to be true, which his reaſon telleth him is falſe; much leſſe is it poſsible for any man to have his reaſon commanded by the will, or at the pleaſure of another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a true ſaying of the Schoolemen, <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas imperat intellectui quoad exercitium, non quoad ſpecificationem,</hi> Mine owne will, or the will of another may command me to thinke upon a matter; but no will or command can conſtraine me to determine otherwiſe then my reaſon teacheth me. Yet <hi>Sir,</hi> I hope your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty will acknowledge, (for your Paper profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth no leſſe) that according to the ſaying of <hi>Ambroſe, Non eſt pudor ad meliora tranſire,</hi> It is neither ſinne nor shame to change to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178715:6"/>better: <hi>Symmachus</hi> in one of his Epiſtles (I think to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> &amp; <hi>Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) alledgeth al thoſe motives from education, from preſcription of time, from worldly proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, and the flourishing condition of the Roman Empire, and from the Lawes of the Land, to perſwade them to conſtancy in the ancient Pagan profeſſion of the Romans, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the imbracing of the Chriſtian Faith. The like reaſons were uſed by the Iewes for <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and may be uſed both for Popery and for the Papacy it ſelfe, againſt the reformation of Religion, and Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and therefore can have no more ſtrength againſt a Change now, than they had in former times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But your Majeſty may perhaps ſay, That this is <hi>petitio principii,</hi> and nothing elſe but the begging of the Queſtion; and I confeſſe it were ſo, if there can be no Reaſons brought for a Reformation or Change; your Majeſty reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencis the Reformation of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as being done legally, and orderly, and by thoſe who had the Reforming Power: and I doe not deny but it were to be wisht, that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, where there is need, were alwaies Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in that manner, and by ſuch power, and that it were not committed to the Prelats, who have greateſt need to be reformed themſelves, nor left to the multitude, whom God ſtirreth up
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:178715:7"/>when Princes are negligent: Thus did <hi>Iacob</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his owne Family, <hi>Moſes</hi> deſtroyed the golden Calfe, the good Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> reformed the Church in their time: but that ſuch Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation hath been perfect, I cannot admit. <hi>Aſa</hi> tooke away Idolatry, but his Reformation was not perfect; for <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> removed the high Places, yet was not his Reformation perfect, for it was <hi>Hezekiah</hi> that brake the braſen Serpent, &amp; <hi>Ioſiah</hi> deſtroyed the Idol-Temples, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beareth this Elogie, <hi>That like unto him there was no King before him.</hi> It is too well knowne that the Reformation of K. <hi>Hen:</hi> 8. was moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in the Eſſentials of Doctrine, Worship, and Government; And although it proceeded by ſome degrees afterward, yet the Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was never reformed, the head was changed, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus non Dominium;</hi> and the whole limbs of the Antichriſtian Hierarchy retained, upon what ſnares and temptations of Avarice, and Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the great Enchanters of the Clergy, I need not expreſſe. It was a hard ſaying of <hi>Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Malleus Groſted of Lincolne,</hi> That Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not to be expected, <hi>niſi in ore gladii cruentandi:</hi> yet this I may ſay, that the Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicean lukewarmneſſe of reformation here, hath been matter of continued complaints to many of the Godly in this Kingdom; occaſion of more ſchiſme, and ſeparation then ever was heard of in any other Church;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:178715:7"/>and of unſpeakable grief, &amp; ſorrow to other Churches, which God did bleſſe with greater purity of reformation. The glory of this great worke we hope is reſerved for your Majeſty, that to your comfort, and everlaſting fame the praiſe of godly <hi>Ioſiah</hi> may be made yours; which yet will be no diſpraiſe to your royall Father, or <hi>Edward</hi> 6. or any other religious Princes before you; none of them having ſo faire an opportunity as is now by the ſupreme providence put into your Royall hands. My ſoule trembleth to thinke and foreſee, what may be the event, if this opportunity be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. I will neither uſe the words of <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, Eſth.</hi> 4.14. nor what <hi>Savanarola</hi> told ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Charles,</hi> becauſe I hope better things from your Majeſty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the Argument brought by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty (which I believe none of your Doctors, had they been all about you, could more briefly, and yet ſo fully, and ſtrongly have expreſſed) [<hi>That nothing was retained in this Church but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it was deduced from the Apoſtles in the conſtant univerſall practiſe of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church; and that it was of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as by the alteration of it, We should deprive our ſelves of the lawfulneſſe of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> (I thinke your Majeſty meanes a lawfull Miniſtry) <hi>and then how the Sacraments can be adminiſtred, is eaſie to judge.</hi>] I humbly offer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:178715:8"/>theſe conſiderations:</p>
            <p>Firſt, what was not in the times of the Apoſtles, cannot be deduced from them: We ſay in <hi>Scotland, It cannot be brought But, that is not there Ben;</hi> but (not to inſiſt now on a Liturgie, and things of that kind) there was no ſuch Hierarchy, no ſuch difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a Bishop, and a Presbyter in the times of the Apoſtles, and therefore it cannot thence be deduced; for I conceive it to be as cleare as if it were written with a ſun-beame, that Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, and Bishop are to the Apoſtles one, and the ſame thing, no majority no inequality or difference of office, power, or degree betwixt the one, and the other, but a meere identity in all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Apoſtles intending to ſet downe the Offices, and Officers of the Church, and ſpeaking ſo often of them, and of their gifts and duties, and that, not upon occaſion, but of ſet purpoſe; doe neither expreſſe, nor imply any ſuch Paſtor, or Bishop as hath power over other Paſtors, although it be true, that they have diſtinctly and particularly expreſt the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, gifts, and duties of the meaneſt Officers, ſuch as Deacons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in the Miniſtery of the New Teſtament there is a comely, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; divine order, and ſubordination; one kind of Miniſters both ordinary, &amp; extraordinary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing placed in degree, and dignity one before another, as the Apoſtles firſt, the Evangeliſts, Paſtors, Doctors, &amp;c. in their owne ranks:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:178715:8"/>but we cannot find in Offices of the ſame kind, that one hath majority of power, or priority of degree before another; no Apoſtle above other Apoſtles (unleſſe in morall reſpects) no Evangeliſt above other Evangeliſts; of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con above other Deacons; why then a Paſtor above other Paſtors? In all other ſorts of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ordinary, and extraodinary a parity in their owne kind, onely in the office of Paſtor an inequality.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the whole power, and all the parts of the Miniſtry, which are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>the power of order and juriſdiction,</hi> are by the Apoſtles declared to be common to the Presbyter and Bishop: And that <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.16, 17. the gradation in matter of Diſcipline, or Church-cenſures, is from one, to two, or more; and if he shall neglect them, tell it to the Church, he ſaith not, tell it to the Bishop; there is no place left to a retrogradation from more to one, were he never ſo eminent. If theſe conſiderations doe not ſatisfie, your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty may have more, or the ſame further cleared.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Secondly, I do humbly deſire Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to take notice of the fallacy of that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from the practice of the Primitive Church, and the univerſall conſent of the Fathers. It is the Argument of the Papiſts for ſuch tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions as no Orthodox Divine will admit. The Law, and Teſtimony muſt be the Rule. We can have no certaine knowledge of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:178715:9"/>univerſall practice of the Church for many yeares. <hi>Euſebius</hi> the prime Hiſtorian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ſo much, The learned <hi>Ioſephus Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger</hi> teſtifieth, that from the end of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles untill a good time after, no certainty can be had from Eccleſiaſticall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors about Church matters. It is true, <hi>Diotrephes</hi> ſought the preheminence in the Apoſtles times, and the myſtery of iniquity did then begin to work; and no doubt in after-times ſome puffed up with Ambition, and others overtaken with weakneſſe, endeavoured alteration of Church Government, but that all the learned and godly of thoſe times conſented to ſuch a change as is talked of afterwards, will never be proved.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Thirdly, I will never think that Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will deny the lawfulneſſe of a Miniſtery, &amp; the due adminiſtration of the Sacraments in the Reformed Churches, which have no Dioceſian Bishops, ſith it is not onely manifeſt by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but a great many of the ſtrongeſt Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Epiſcopacy, doe confeſſe, that Presbyters may ordaine other Presbyters; &amp; that Baptiſme adminiſtred by a private perſon, wanting a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Calling, or by a Midwife, or by a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, although not ordained by a Bishop, are one, and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Concerning the other Argument taken from Your Majeſties <hi>Coronation Oath;</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that both in the taking, and keeping of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:178715:9"/>an Oath (ſo ſacred a thing is it, and ſo high a point of Religion,) much tenderneſſe is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and farre be it from us, who deſire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our owne Solemne Oath, to preſſe Your Majeſty with the violation of Yours. Yet Sir, I will crave your leave, in all humbleneſſe and ſincerity to lay before Your Majeſties eyes this one thing, (which perhaps might require a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dicourſe) that although no humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can diſpenſe with an Oath, <hi>Quia Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio juramenti pertinet ad forum Divinum;</hi> yet in ſome caſes it cannot be denied but the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Oath ceaſeth: As when we ſwear homage and obedience to our Lord and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, who afterwards ceaſeth to be our Lord and Superiour; for then the formall cauſe of the Oath is taken away, and therefore the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Sublata cauſa tollitur effectus; ſublato relato, tollitur Correlatum.</hi> Or when any Oath hath a ſpeciall reference to the benefit of thoſe to whom I make the promiſe, if we have their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or conſent, the obligation ceaſeth; becauſe all ſuch Oaths from the nature of the thing, doe include a condition. When the Parliaments of both Kingdomes, have covenanted for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing or altering of a Law, Your Majeſties Oath doth not binde You, or Your Conſcience to the obſerving of it; otherwiſe no Lawes could be altered by the Legiſlative Power. This I conceive hath been the ground of removing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:178715:10"/>Epiſcopall Governement in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of removing the Bishops out of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England.</hi> And I aſſure my ſelfe, that Your Majeſty did not intend at the taking of Your Oath, that although both Houſes of Parliament should find an alteration neceſſary, although, (which God Almighty avert) You should looſe Your Selfe, &amp; your Poſterity, and Crown, that You would never conſent to the abolishing of ſuch a Law. If Your Majeſty ſtill object, that the matter of the Oath is neceſſary and immutable; that doth not belong to this, but to the former Argument.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I have but one word more concerning Your Piety to Your Royall Father, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of happy Memory, with which Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty does conclude. Your Majeſty knowes that King <hi>Iames</hi> never admitted Epiſcopacy upon Divine Right; That His Majeſty did ſweare and ſubſcribe to the Doctrine, Worship, and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Scotland;</hi> that in the Preface of the latter Edition of <hi>Baſilicon Doron,</hi> His Majeſty gives an honourable teſtimony to thoſe that loved, better the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, than the pomp and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that he conceived the Prelats to ſavour of the Popish Hierarchy, and that (could his Ghoſt now ſpeake to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty) He would not adviſe your Majeſty to run ſuch hazards for thoſe men who will chuſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:178715:10"/>rather to pull downe your Throne with their own ruine, than that they perish alone. The Lord give your Majeſty a wiſe and diſcerning Spirit to chuſe that in time which is right.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuny</hi> 3. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Alex: Henderſon, <hi>A Reply to his Anſwer to My firſt Paper, Iune</hi> 6. 1646.</head>
            <head type="sub">His MAJESTIES ſecond Paper.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Henderſon,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF it had been the Honour of the Cauſe which I looked after, I would not have undertaken to put Pen to Paper, or ſingly to have maintained this Argument againſt you (whoſe Anſwer to my former Paper is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, without other proofs, to juſtifie My opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of your abilities) but, it being meerly (as you know) for my particular ſatisfaction, I aſſure you that a Diſputation of well choſen Divines, would be moſt effectuall; and, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:178715:11"/>you cannot but grant, that I muſt beſt know, how My ſelfe may be beſt ſatisfied, for certainly My Taſte cannot be guided by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Mans Palate, and indeed I will ſay, that when it comes (as it muſt) to Probations, I muſt have either <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Bookes</hi> to cleare the Allegations, or it will be impoſſible to give Me ſatisfaction: The fore-ſeeing of which, made Me at firſt (for the ſaving of Time) deſire that ſome of thoſe Divines, which I gave you in a Lift, might be ſent for.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning your ſecond Section, I were much too blame, if I should not ſubmit to that ſaying of S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> which you mention, for I would be unwilling to be found leſſe ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then you shew your ſe;lfe to be in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of it; wherefore my Reply is, that as I shall not be ashamed <hi>to change for the better,</hi> ſo I muſt ſee that it is <hi>better</hi> before I <hi>change,</hi> otherwiſe inconſtancy in this were both ſinne and shame; and remember (what your ſelfe hath learnedly enforced) that <hi>no mans Reaſon can be commanded by another mans Wil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Your third begins, but I cannot ſay that it goes on, with that Ingenuity, which the other did; for I doe not underſtand, how thoſe <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> cited out of the Old Teſtament do any way prove that the way of <hi>Reformation,</hi> which I commend, hath not been the moſt perfect, or, that any other is lawfull, thoſe having been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:178715:11"/>all by the <hi>Regall Authority;</hi> and becauſe <hi>Henry the Eights Reformation</hi> was not perfect, will it prove that of K. <hi>Edward</hi> and Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> to be unperfect? I believe a new <hi>moode</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> muſt be found out to forme a <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme,</hi> whereby to prove that: but however, you are miſtaken; for, no man who truely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the <hi>English Reformation,</hi> will derive it from <hi>Henry the Eight;</hi> for he onely gave the occaſion; it was his <hi>Sonne</hi> who began, and Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that perfected it; nor did I ever averre, that the beginning of any Humane A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was perfect, no more then you can prove that <hi>God hath ever given approbation to Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes to Reforme the Negligence of Princes:</hi> For, you know, there is much Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Permiſsion,</hi> and <hi>Approbation:</hi> But all this time; I find no <hi>Reaſons</hi> (according to your Promiſe) for a <hi>Reformation,</hi> or Change) I mean ſince Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time.) As for your <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum Malleus</hi> his ſaying; it is well you come of with it, <hi>[yet this I may ſay]</hi> for it ſeems to imply, as if you neither ought nor would juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that <hi>bloudy ungodly ſaying:</hi> and for your comparing our <hi>Reformation</hi> here to the <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean lukewarmeneſſe,</hi> proved by <hi>Complaints, Grievings, &amp;c.</hi> all that doth, and but unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, <hi>Petere principium;</hi> nor can Generalls ſatisfie Me; for, you muſt firſt prove, that thoſe Men had reaſon to complaine, thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:178715:12"/>Churches to be Grieved, and how we were truely the Cauſers of this ſchiſme and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as for thoſe words which you will not uſe, I will not anſwer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Here indeed you truly repeat the firſt of My two maine Arguments; but by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, you take (as I conceive) a wrong way to convince Me; It is I muſt make good the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative,</hi> for I believe a <hi>Negative</hi> cannot be proved; Inſtead of which, if you had made appeare the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> in the <hi>Primitive times,</hi> you had done much; for I doe averre, that this <hi>Government</hi> was never Practiſed before <hi>Calvin's</hi> time; the <hi>Affirmative</hi> of which, I leave you to prove; My taske, being to shew the <hi>lawfulneſſe,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsion of Epiſcopacy,</hi> and, as I believe, the <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity</hi> of it: For doing whereof, I muſt have ſuch Books as I shall call for; which poſſibly upon peruſall, may, one way or other, give Me ſatisfaction; but I cannot abſolutely promiſe it, without the Aſſiſtance of ſome learned Man, whom I can truſt, to find out all ſuch Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as I have uſe of: wherefore blame Me not, if time be unneceſſarily loſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Now for the <hi>fallaciouſneſſe</hi> of My <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (to My knowledge) it was never My <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> nor doe I confeſſe to have begun now; For if the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and the <hi>univerſall conſent of the Fathers,</hi> be not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:178715:12"/>a convincing <hi>Argument,</hi> when the <hi>Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> is doubtfull, I know nothing; For, if this be not, then of <hi>neceſsity</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of private Spirits</hi> muſt bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: the which contradicts Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. and is the <hi>Mother</hi> of all <hi>Sects,</hi> and will (if not prevented) bring theſe <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> into <hi>confuſion:</hi> And to ſay, that an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is ill, becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſe it, or, that ſuch a thing is good, becauſe it is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not weigh with Me, until you prove, theſe to be <hi>infallible,</hi> or that to maintaine <hi>no Truth:</hi> And how <hi>Diotrephes ambition</hi> (who directly oppoſed the <hi>Apoſtle S. Iohn</hi>) can be an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> I doe not underſtand.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When I am made a <hi>Iudge</hi> over the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches,</hi> then, and not before, will I cenſure their <hi>Actions;</hi> as you muſt prove, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I confeſſe it, that <hi>Presbyters without a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, may lawfully ordain other Presbyters:</hi> And as for the Adminiſtration of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> as I thinke none will ſay, that a Woman can law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, or Duly adminiſter it, though when done, it be <hi>valid;</hi> ſo none ought to doe it, but a lawfull <hi>Presbyter,</hi> whom you cannot deny, but to be abſolutely neceſſary for the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. You make a learned ſuccinct diſcourſe of <hi>Oathes</hi> in generall, and their ſeverall <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:178715:13"/>to which I fully agree; intending, in the particular now in queſtion, to be guided by your owne <hi>Rule,</hi> which is <hi>[when any Oath hath a ſpeciall reference to the Benefit of thoſe to whom I make the Promiſe, if we have their deſire, or conſent, the Obligation ceaſeth]</hi> Now, it muſt be knowne, <hi>to whom</hi> this Oath hath reference, and to <hi>whoſe Benefit?</hi> the Anſwer is cleare, onely to the <hi>Church of England;</hi> as by the <hi>Record</hi> will be plainly made appeare; and you much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in alleaging that the two <hi>Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (eſpecially as they are now conſtituted) can have this <hi>Diſobligatory Power,</hi> for, (beſides that they are not named in it) I am confident to made it clearly appear to you, that this <hi>Church</hi> never did ſubmit, nor was ſubordinate to them; and that it was onely the <hi>King and Clergy,</hi> who made the <hi>Reformation,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> meerly ſerving to help to give the <hi>Civill Sanction:</hi> all this being proved (of which I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) it muſt neceſſarily follow, that it is onely the <hi>Church of England</hi> (in whoſe favour I took this Oath) that can releaſe me from it: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the <hi>Church of England</hi> (being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Aſſembled) shall declare that I am free, <hi>then,</hi> and not before, I ſhall eſteeme My ſelfe ſo.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To your laſt, concerning the <hi>King my Father,</hi> of happy and famous Memory, both for his <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Learning;</hi> I muſt tell you,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:178715:13"/>that I had the happineſſe, to know him much better then you; wherefore I deſire you, not to be too confident, in the knowledge of his Opinions; For, I dare ſay, should his <hi>Ghoſt now ſpeake,</hi> he would tell you, that a <hi>Bloudy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> was never lawfull, as not warranted by <hi>Gods word,</hi> and that <hi>Preces &amp; la chrymoe ſunt Arma Eccleſioe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. To conclude, having replied to all your Paper, I cannot but obſerve to you, that you have given Me no Anſwer to My laſt <hi>Quaere;</hi> it may be you are (as <hi>Chaucer</hi> ſayes) like the <hi>People of England, what they not like, they never underſtand:</hi> but in earneſt, that <hi>Queſtion</hi> is ſo pertinent to the Purpoſe in hand, that it will, much ſerve for My ſatisfaction; and beſides it may be uſefull for other things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune</hi> 6. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:178715:14"/>
            <head>For His Majeſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Alex: Henderſon's</hi> ſecond Paper.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſmaller the encouragements be, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the ſucceſſe, (which how ſmall they are, your Majeſty well knowes:) the more apparent, and, I hope, the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will my obedience be, in that which in all humility I now go about, at your Majeſties Command: yet while I conſider, that the way of man is not in himſelfe; nor is it in man that walketh, to direct his owne ſteps; and when I remember how many ſupplications, with ſtrong crying and teares, have been openly and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret offered up in your Majeſties behalfe, unto God that heareth prayer, I have no reaſon to deſpaire of a bleſſed ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I have been averſe, from a diſputation of Divines,
<list>
                  <item>1. For ſaving of time; which the preſent exigence &amp; extremity of affairs, make more then ordinarily pretious; While <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes</hi> at <hi>Syracuſe</hi> was drawing this Figures
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:178715:14"/>&amp; Circlings in the ſand, <hi>Marcellus</hi> interupted his demonſtration.</item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe the common reſult of Diſputes of this kinde, anſwerable to the prejudicate opinions of the Parties, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Victory then Verity; while <hi>tanquam ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tativi Dialectici,</hi> they ſtudy more to overcome their adverſe Party, then to be overcome of Truth, although this be the moſt glorious Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</item>
                  <item>3. When I was commanded to come hither; no ſuch thing was propoſed to me, nor expected by me. I never judged ſo meanly of the Cauſe, nor ſo highly of my ſelfe, as to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it upon ſuch weakneſſe. Much more might be ſpoken to this purpoſe; but I forbeare.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I will not further trouble your Majeſty with that which is contained in the ſecond Section, hoping that your Majeſty will no more inſiſt upon <hi>Education, preſcription of Time, &amp;c.</hi> which are ſufficient to prevent Admiration, but (which your Majeſty acknowledges) muſt give place to Reaſon, and are no ſure ground of reſolution of our Faith, in any point to be believed: although it be true that the moſt part of men make theſe &amp; the like, to be the ground and rule of their Faith: an Evidence, that their Faith is not a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine faith, but an humane Credulity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning <hi>Reformation of Religion</hi> in the third Section; I had need of a Preface to ſo thorny a Theame, as your Majeſty hath brought me upon; 1. For <hi>the Reforming power,</hi> it is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:178715:15"/>conceived, when a Generall Defection, like a deluge, hath covered the whole face of the Church, ſo that ſcarcely the tops of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains doe appeare, a Generall Councell is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; but, becauſe that can hardly be obtained, ſeverall Kingdomes (which we ſee was done, at the time of the Reformation) are to reforme themſelves, and that by the Authority of their Prince, &amp; Magiſtrates: if the Prince or ſupreme Magiſtrate be unwilling, then may the inferior Magiſtrate, and the People, being before rightly informed in the grounds of Religion, lawfully Reforme, with in their owne Sphere; and if the light shine upon all, or the major part, they may, after all other meanes aſſayed, make a Publique Reformation. This, before this time, I never wrote or ſpoke; yet the Maintainers of the Doctrine, conceive that they are able to make it good. But, <hi>Sir,</hi> were I worthy to give advice to Your Majeſty, or to the Kings and ſupreme Powers on Earth, my humble Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would be, that they should draw the minds, tongues, and pens of the learned, to diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout other matters, then the power or Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of Kings &amp; Princes; and in this kind, your Majeſty hath ſuffered and loſt more, then will eaſily be reſtored to your ſelfe or your Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for along time. It is not denied but the prime Reforming power, is in Kings and Princes, <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus—deficientibus,</hi> it comes to the inferior Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:178715:15"/>
               <hi>Quibus Deficientibus,</hi> it deſcendeth to the Body of the People, ſuppoſing that there is a neceſſity of Reformation, and that by no meanes it can be obtained of their Superiors. It is true that ſuch a Reformation, is more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in reſpect of the Inſtruments, &amp; manner of Procedure; yet for the moſt part, more pure and perfect in relation to the effect &amp; product. And for this end did I cite the Examples of old of Reformation by Regall Authority, of which none was perfect, in the ſecond way of perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except that of <hi>Ioſiah.</hi> Concerning the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Groſtead,</hi> whom the <hi>Cardinals at Rome</hi> confeſt to be a more Godly man, than any of themſelves; it was his Complaint, and Predic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what was likely to enſue, not his deſire, or Election, if Reformation could have been obtained, in the ordinary way. I might bring two unpartial Witneſſes, <hi>Iewell</hi> and <hi>Bilſon,</hi> both famous English Bishops, to prove, that the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults &amp; troubles raiſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> at the time of Reformation, were to be imputed to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts oppoſing of the Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine &amp; Diſcipline, as an Heretical Innovation; and not to be aſcribed to the Nobility, or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who under God, were the Inſtruments of it; intending &amp; ſeeking nothing, but the purging out of Errour, and ſetling of the Truth. 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I conceive, whether it was begun or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:178715:16"/>not, in K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. time, it was not finished by Q. <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> the Father ſtirred the humors of the diſeaſed Church; but neither the Sonne nor the Daughter (although we have great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to bleſſe God for both) did purge them out perfectly: This Perfection is yet reſerved for your Majeſty: Where it is ſaid, <hi>that all this time I bring no Reaſons, for a further Change;</hi> the fourth Section, of my laſt Paper, hath many hints of Reaſons againſt <hi>Epiſcopall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> with an offer of more, or clearing of thoſe, which your Majeſty hath not thought fit to take notice of. And learned men, have obſerved many Defects in that Reformation: As that the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (for about this is the Queſtion now) is not builded upon the foundation of Chriſt and the Apoſtles; which they at leaſt cannot deny, who profeſſe Church-Government to be Mutable and Ambulatory, and ſuch were the greater part of Archbishops &amp; Bishops in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> contenting themſelves with the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Church, and the Authority and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of Princes, till of late, that ſome few have pleaded it to be <hi>Iure Divino:</hi> That the English Reformation hath not perfectly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out the Roman Leaven; which is one of the Reaſons, that have given ground, to them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring of this Church, to be Church of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaea,</hi> as being neither hot nor cold, neither Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:178715:16"/>nor Reformed, but of a lukewarme tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, betwixt the two: That it hath depraved the Diſcipline of the Church, by conforming of it to the Civill Policy: That it hath added many Church Offices, higher &amp; lower, unto thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the Sonne of God; which is as unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as to take away offices warranted by the Divine Inſtitution: And other the like, which have moved ſome, to apply this ſaying, to the Church of England; <hi>Multi ad perfectionem perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nirent, niſijam ſe perveniſſe crederent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In my Anſwer to the firſt of your Majeſties many Arguments, I brought a Breviate of ſome Reaſons to prove, <hi>that a Bishop and Presbyter, are one and the ſame in Scripture:</hi> from which, by neceſſary conſequence, I did inferre the <hi>negative; Therefore,</hi> no difference in Scripture between a Bishop and a Presbyter; the one name ſignifying, <hi>Induſtriam Curae Paſtoralis;</hi> the other, <hi>Sapientiae Maturitatem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beda.</hi> And whereas your Majeſty averres, that <hi>Presbyterian Government was never prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, before Calvin's time:</hi> your Majeſty knowes, the common objection of the Papiſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Reformed Churches; where was your Church, your Reformation, your Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, before <hi>Luther's</hi> time? One part of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Anſwer is, <hi>that it was from the beginning, and is to be found in Scripture:</hi> The ſame I affirme of Presbyterian-Government: And for proving
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:178715:17"/>of this, the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> have made manifeſt, that <hi>the Primitive Chriſtian Church at Ieruſalem was governed by a Presbytery:</hi> while they shew,
<list>
                  <item>1. That the Church of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> conſiſted of more Congregations then one, from the multitude of Believers, from the many Apoſtles, and other Preachers in that Church, and from the diverſity of Languages among the Believers.</item>
                  <item>2. That all thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, were under one Presbyteriall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, becauſe they were, for Government, one Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.22, 26.</item>
               </list> And becauſe that Church was governed by Elders, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.30. which were Elders of that Church, &amp; did meet together for Acts of Government: And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, in that meeting, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. acted not as Apoſtles, but as Elders, ſtating the Queſtion, debating it, in the ordinary way of diſputation; and having, by ſearch of Scripture, found the will of God, they conclude, <hi>It ſeemed good too the Holy Ghoſt and us:</hi> which in the jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement of the learned, may be ſpoken by any Aſſembly, upon like evidence of Scripture. The like Presbyterian Government had place in the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Epheſus, Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, &amp;c.</hi> in the times of the Apoſtles; and after them, for many yeares, when one of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery was made <hi>Epiſcopus Praeſes,</hi> even then, <hi>Communi Presbyterorum Conſilio, Eccleſiae guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome; &amp; Epiſcopos magis conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:178715:17"/>quam Diſpoſitionis Divinae veritate, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris eſſe majores, &amp; in Commune debere Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am regere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Farre be it from me to think ſuch a thought, as that your Majeſty did intend any Fallacy, in your other maine Argument, from Antiquity. As we are to diſtinguish between <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio Operantis, &amp; Conditio Operis,</hi> ſo may we in this caſe conſider the difference between <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Argumentantis, &amp; Conditio Argumenti.</hi> And where your Majeſty argues, that, if your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion be not admitted, we will be forced to give place to the <hi>Interpretation of private Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> which is contrary to the Doctrine of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> and will prove to be of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence, I humbly offer to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by Your Majeſty, what ſome of chief note among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves have taught us, That the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Spirits</hi> whence they proceed, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>private,</hi> in a threefold ſenſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Ratione Perſonae,</hi> if the Interpreter be of a private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Ratione Modi &amp; Medii,</hi> when Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, although not private, uſe not the publique meanes which are neceſſary for finding out the Truth, but follow their owne fancies.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Ratione finis,</hi> when the Interpretation is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as Authenticall to bind others, but is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended onely for our owne private ſatisfaction.</item>
               </list> The firſt is not to be deſpiſed, the ſecond is to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:178715:18"/>exploded, and is condemned by the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> the third ought not to be cenſured: But that Interpretation which is Authenticall, and of ſupreme Authority, which every mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is bound to yeild unto, is of an higher nature. And, although the Generall Councell should reſolve it, &amp; the Conſent of the Fathers should be had unto it, yet there muſt alwaies be place left to the judgment of Diſcretion, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> late Bishop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> beſide divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath learnedly made appeare in his Book, <hi>De Iudice Controverſiarum;</hi> where alſo the Power of Kings in matter of Religion; is ſolidly and unpartially determined. Two words one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I adde; one is, that notwithſtanding all that is pretended from Antiquity, a Bishop hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſole power of Ordination and Juriſdiction, will never be found in <hi>Prime Antiquity.</hi> The other is, that many of the Fathers did, unwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly, bring forth that <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which was conceived in the times of the Apoſtles, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are incompetent Judges in the Queſtion of <hi>Hierarchy.</hi> And upon the other part, the Lights of the Chriſtian Church, at, and ſince the beginning of the Reformation, have diſcovered many ſecrets, concerning the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> which were not knowne to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages: And diverſe of the learned, in the Roman Church, have not feared to pronounce, That, whoſoever denies the true &amp; literall ſenſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:178715:18"/>of many Texts of Scripture, to have been found out in this laſt Age, is unthankfull to God, who hath ſo plentifully powred forth his Spirit upon the Children of this Generation, &amp; ungratefull towards thoſe men, who with ſo great paines, ſo happy ſucceſſe, &amp; ſo much benefit to Gods Church, have travailed therein: This might be inſtanced in many places of Scripture: I joyne together <hi>Diotrephes</hi> and the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> the one, as an old example of Church-ambition, which was alſo too palpable in the Apoſtles themſelves; And the other as a cover of Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, afterwards diſcovered; which two, brought forth the <hi>great Myſtery</hi> of the Papacy at laſt.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Although your Maj<hi rend="sup">ſty.</hi> be not made a Judge of the Reformed Churches, yet you ſo farre cenſure them, and their actions, as without Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, in your judgment, they cannot have a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſtery, nor a due Adminiſtration of the Sacraments: Againſt which dangerous &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Opinion, I did alledge what I ſuppoſed, your Majeſty would not have denied,
<list>
                  <item>1. That Presbyters without a Bishop, may Ordaine other Presbyters.</item>
                  <item>2. That Bapatiſme, adminiſtred by ſuch a Presbyter, is another thing than Baptiſme adminiſtred by a private Perſon, or by a Midwife.</item>
               </list> Of the firſt your Majeſty calls for proofe: I told you before, that in Scripture, it is manifeſt, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Neglect not the Gift that is in Thee, which was given Thee by the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:178715:19"/>Propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery;</hi> ſo it is in the English Tranſlation: And the word <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ſo often as it is uſed in the New Teſtament, alwaies ſignifies the <hi>Perſons,</hi> and not the <hi>Office.</hi> And although the Offices of Bishop, and Presbyter were diſtinct; yet doth not the Presbyter derive his power of Order, from the Bishop. The Evangeliſts were inferior to the Apoſtles; yet had they their power, not from the Apoſtles, but from Chriſt: The ſame I affirme of the 70. Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who had their power immediately from Chriſt, no leſſe then the Apoſtles had theirs. It may upon better reaſon be averred, that the Bishops have their power from the Pope, than that Presbyters have their power from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats. It is true, <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid facit, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptâ ordinatione Epiſcopus, quod non facit Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter;</hi> but in the ſame place he proves from Scripture, that <hi>Epiſcopus &amp; Presbyter</hi> are one and the ſame; and therefore when he appropriates Ordination to the Bishop, he ſpeaketh of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated cuſtome of his time. 2. Concerning Baptiſme, a private Perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may performe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Action &amp; Rites both of it and of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt; yet is neither of the two a Sacrament, or hath any efficacy, unleſſe it be done by him that is lawfully called there unto, or by a Perſon made publique &amp; clothed with Authority by Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This Errour in the matter of Baptiſme, is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:178715:19"/>begot by another Errour, of the Abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To that which hath been ſaid, concerning your Majeſties Oath, I shall adde nothing; not being willing to enter upon the Queſtion, of the ſubordination of the Church to the Civill power, whether to King, or Parliament, or both, or to either of them, in their owne place. Such an Headship as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have claimed, and ſuch a ſupremacy as the Houſes of Parliament crave, with Appeales from the ſupreme Eccleſiaſticall Iudicature to them as ſet over the Church, in the ſame line of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination, I doe utterly diſclaime upon ſuch Reaſons as give my ſelfe ſatisfaction, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no man shall be more willing to ſubmit to Civill Powers, each one in their owne place; and more unwilling to make any trouble then my ſelfe; Onely concerning the application of the Generalls of an <hi>Oath,</hi> to the particular caſe now in hand; under favour, I conceive not how the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is or ought to be principally intended, in your <hi>Oath:</hi> For, although they were eſteemed to be the Repreſentative Church, yet even that is for the benefit of the Church Collective, <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> being <hi>Suprema Lex,</hi> and to be principally intended. Your Majeſty knowes it was ſo in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the like alteration was made. And, if nothing of this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:178715:20"/>kind can be done with the conſent of the Clergy, what Reformation can be expected in <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe? It is not to be expected, that the Pope, or Prelate will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their owne ruine.</p>
            <p n="8">8. I will not preſume upon any ſecret know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Opinions held by the King, your Majeſties Father, of famous Memory; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much better knowne to your Majeſty. I did onely produce, what was profeſt by him, before the world: And although Prayers, and Teares be the Armes of the Church; yet, it is neither acceptable to God, nor conducible for Kings &amp; Princes, to force the Church to put on theſe Armes: Nor could I ever heare a reaſon, why a neceſſary Defenſive Warre againſt unjuſt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is unlawfull, although it be joyned with offence and invaſion which is intended for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but ſo that Armes are layed downe when the Offenſive War ceaſeth: by which it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that the War on the other ſide, was, in the nature thereof, Defenſive.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Concerning the forcing of Conſcience, which I pretermitted in my other Paper, I am forced now, but without forcing of Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, to ſpeake of. Our Conſcience may be ſaid to be forced; either by our ſelves, or by others. By our ſelves,
<list>
                  <item>1. when we ſtop the eare of our Conſcience and will not hearken, or give place to information, reſolving obſtinately, <hi>Neſi
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:178715:20"/>perſuaſeris, perſuadebis;</hi> which is no leſſe then a reſiſting of the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; the hardning of our hearts.</item>
                  <item>2. Or when we ſtop the mouth and ſuppreſſe the clamours of our Conſcience; reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rather to ſuffer the worme to gnaw, &amp; the fire to burne inwardly, them to make profeſſion of that we are convinced to be Truth.</item>
                  <item>3. Or when we ſeare our Conſcience, as with an hot Iron, that it becometh ſenſleſſe; which is the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of the former: unto which is oppoſed, the truly Tender Conſcience; ſuch as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> had, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.19.</item>
               </list> Againe, 1. Our Conſcience is ſaid to be forced by others; when they obtrude upon us what is in it ſelfe evill and unlawfull; which if we admit, againſt our owne Conſcience, we ſinne two waies; one is, by doing that which is in it ſelfe evill and unlawfull; the other is, by doing it againſt a dictate of Conſcience, which is a contempt of God, whoſe Vicegerent it is. 2 Or when others urge us to doe that which is in it ſelfe good, or may lawfully be done, but through errour of Conſcience, we judge it to be evill, and unlawfull: in this caſe, if we doe not that which is preſt upon us, we ſinne, becauſe the thing is good and lawfull: And if we doe it, we ſinne; becauſe we doe againſt our Conſcience. Which in this caſe bindeth, but obligeth not: And yet there is a way to eſcape out of this labyrinth, it being repugnant to the equity of the will of God to lay a Neceſſity
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:178715:21"/>of ſinning upon any man: The onely way is, to lay aſide ſuch a Conſcience; it being a part of the Old man: Which we are commanded to put off; otherwiſe, we being ſufficiently informed, and yet cleaving to our old errour, we rather doe violence to our Conſcience our ſelves then ſuffer violence from others. The Application, for Anſwering the <hi>Quaere,</hi> I leave to your Majeſty.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>June 17. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Alex: Henderſon, In Reply to his ſecond Paper, <hi>Iune.</hi> 22. 1646.</head>
            <head type="sub">His MAIESTIES third Paper.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I It were arrogance, beſides loſſe of time, in Me to vie <hi>preambles</hi> with you; For, it is the <hi>truth</hi> I ſeek, and neither <hi>praiſe,</hi> nor <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> wherefore I shall only inſiſt upon thoſe things which are meerly neceſſary to my owne ſatisfaction; in order to which, I deſired the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of ſome <hi>Divines;</hi> whereupon I will inſiſt no further, ſave onely to wish, that you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:178715:21"/>may not (as I have knowne many Men doe) <hi>looſe</hi> time by being miſtaken in the way to <hi>ſave</hi> it, wherein I have onely ſought to disburden My ſelfe, but to lay no blame upon you, and ſo I leave it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor will I ſay more of the ſecond then this, that I am glad you have ſo well approved of what I have ſaid concerning My <hi>Education</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> but then remember, that <hi>another Mans will,</hi> is at leaſt, as weake a ground, to build My Faith upon, as My former <hi>Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In this there are two points; Firſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Reforming power,</hi> then anent the <hi>English Reformation;</hi> For the firſt, I confeſſe you now ſpeake clearly, which before you did but darkly mention, wherein I shall mainly differ with you, untill you shall shew Me better reaſons: yet thus farre I will goe along with you, that when a <hi>Generall Councell</hi> cannot be had, ſeverall <hi>Kingdomes</hi> may <hi>reforme</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (which is learnedly and fully proved by the late <hi>Arch-Bishop of Canterbury</hi> in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation againſt <hi>Fisher</hi>) but, that the <hi>inferior Magiſtrates</hi> or <hi>People</hi> (take it which way you will) have this <hi>power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> I utterly deny; For which, by your favour, you have yet made no ſufficient proofe, to My judgement; Indeed, if you could have brought, or can bring autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Scripture, for this opinion, I would and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:178715:22"/>will, yet, with all reverence ſubmit; but as for <hi>your Examples, out of the Old Teſtament,</hi> in My mind, they rather make for, than againſt Me, all thoſe <hi>reformations</hi> being made by <hi>Kings;</hi> and it is a good <hi>preanable</hi> (though I will not ſay <hi>convîncing</hi>) <hi>Argument,</hi> that if God would have approved of a <hi>popular reforming way,</hi> there were <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſufficiently neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and ill to have made ſuch examples by; but by the contrary, the 16. <hi>Chap. of Numbers</hi> shewes clearly, how God <hi>diſapproves</hi> of ſuch courſes: but I forget this Aſſertion is to be proved by you; yet I may put you in the way, wherefore let me tell you, that this <hi>pretended power</hi> in the <hi>People,</hi> muſt (as all others) either be directly, or elſe declaratorily by approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, given by God; which, as ſoon as you can doe, I ſubmit; Otherwiſe your prove nothing: For the citing of private Mens opinions (more then as they concurre with <hi>the generall conſent of the Church</hi> in their time) weighs little with Me, it being too well known, that <hi>Rebels never wanted Writers to maintain their unjuſt actions;</hi> and though I much reverence Bishop <hi>Iewels</hi> memory, I never thought him <hi>infallible;</hi> for <hi>Bilſon</hi> I remember well what opinion the <hi>King</hi> My <hi>Father</hi> had of him for thoſe Opinions, and how He shewed him ſome favour in hope of his <hi>recantation,</hi> (as His good nature made him do many things of that kind) but whether he did,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:178715:22"/>or not, I cannot ſay: To conclude this point, untill you shall prove this <hi>poſition</hi> by the <hi>word of God,</hi> (as I will <hi>Regall Authority</hi>) I shall think all <hi>popular Reformation,</hi> little better than <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions;</hi> for, I hold that <hi>no Authority is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full but that which is either directly given, or</hi> at leaſt, <hi>approved by God.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Concerning the <hi>English Reformation,</hi> the firſt reaſon you bring why Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did not finish it, is, <hi>becauſe she tooke not away Epiſcopacy,</hi> the <hi>hints of reaſon againſt which Government,</hi> you ſay <hi>I take no notice of;</hi> now I thought it was ſufficient no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, yea and anſwer too, when I told you, a <hi>negative</hi> (as I conceived) <hi>could not be proved,</hi> and that it was for Me to prove the <hi>affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> which I shall either doe, or yeild the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, as ſoone as I shall be aſſiſted with <hi>Bookes,</hi> or ſch <hi>Men</hi> of My opinion, who, like you, have a Library in their braine: And ſo I muſt leave this particular, untill I be furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with <hi>means</hi> to put it to an <hi>iſſue;</hi> which had been ſooner done, if I could have had My will: indeed your ſecond well proved, is moſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, which is, that <hi>the English Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is not builded upon the foundation of Chriſt and the Apoſtles;</hi> but I conceive your probation of this, doubly defective; for firſt, albeit our <hi>Archbishops</hi> and <hi>Bishops</hi> should have profeſſed <hi>Church-government</hi> to be <hi>mutable &amp; ambulatory, I</hi> conceive it not ſufficient to prove
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:178715:23"/>your Aſſertion: and ſecondly, I am confident you cannot prove, that moſt of them maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this <hi>walking</hi> poſition, (for ſome particulars muſt not conclude the generall) for which you muſt find much better Arguments than their being content with the <hi>Conſtitution of the Church,</hi> and the <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>munificence of Princes,</hi> or you will fall extreamly short: As for the <hi>retaining</hi> of <hi>the Roman leven,</hi> you muſt prove it, as well as ſay it, elſe you ſay little: But that the conforming of the <hi>Church diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> to the <hi>civill policy,</hi> should be a depraving of it, I abſolutely deny; for I averre, that without it, the <hi>Church</hi> can neither flourish, nor be happy: And for your laſt inſtance, you shall doe well to shew the prohibition of our <hi>Saviour</hi> againſt addition of more Officers in the <hi>Church</hi> than he named; and yet in one ſence I doe not conceive that the <hi>Church of England</hi> hath added any; for, an <hi>Archbishop</hi> is onely a diſtinction for <hi>order</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> not a <hi>new Officer,</hi> and ſo of the reſt; and of this kind, I believe there are diverſe now in <hi>Scotland</hi> which you will not condemne, as the <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Aſſemblies,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Where you find a <hi>Bishop,</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in Scripture, to be one and the ſame (which I deny to be alwaies ſo) it is in the <hi>Apoſtles time;</hi> now I think to prove the Order of <hi>Bishops</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that the name
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:178715:23"/>was chiefly altered, in reverence to thoſe who were immediately choſen by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, in their time, they cauſed diverſe to be called ſo, as <hi>Barnabas</hi> and others) ſo that, I believe, this Argument makes little for you: As for your proofe of the antiquity of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government,</hi> it is well that the <hi>Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines at Weſtminſter</hi> can doe more then <hi>Euſebius</hi> could, and I shall believe, when I ſee it; for, your former Paper affirmes, that thoſe times were very darke for matter of fact, and will be ſo ſtill for Me if there be no clearer Arguments to prove it, then thoſe you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for, becauſe there were <hi>diverſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in Ieruſalem;</hi> ergo, <hi>what?</hi> are there not <hi>divers Parishes in one Dioceſs?</hi> (your two firſt I anſwer but as one Argument) and becauſe the <hi>Apoſtles met with thoſe of the inferior Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, for Acts of Government;</hi> what then? even ſo in theſe times doe the <hi>Deanes and Chapters,</hi> and many times thoſe of the <hi>inferior Clergy</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the <hi>Bishops;</hi> but I hope you will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſay, that there was an equality between <hi>the Apoſtles and other Presbyters,</hi> which not being, doth (in My judgment) quite invalidate theſe Arguments: And if you can ſay no more for the <hi>Churches of Corinth, Epheſus, Theſſalonica, &amp;c.</hi> then you have for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> it will gaine no ground on Me; As for S. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> it is well knowne that he was no great
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:178715:24"/>Friend to <hi>Bishops,</hi> as being none himſelfe, yet take him altogether, and you will find that he makes a cleer diſtinction between a <hi>Bishop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> as your ſelf confeſſes; but the truth is, he was angry with thoſe who maintained <hi>Deacons</hi> to be equall to <hi>Presbyters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. I am well ſatisfied with the explanation of your meaning concerning the word <hi>Fallacy,</hi> though I thinke to have had reaſon for ſaying what I did: But by your favour, I doe not conceive that you have anſwered the ſtrength of my Argument, for when you, and I differ upon the <hi>interpretation of Scripture,</hi> and I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to the <hi>Practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and <hi>the univerſall conſent of the Fathers,</hi> to be judge between us, me thinks you should either find a fitter, or ſubmit to what I offer; neither of which (to My underſtanding) you have yet done; nor have you shewne how, waving thoſe Iudges I appeale unto, the miſchiefe, of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation by <hi>private Spirits,</hi> can be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Indeed, if I cannot prove by <hi>antiquity,</hi> that <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> belongs to <hi>Bishops,</hi> (thereby cleerly diſtinguishing them from other <hi>Presbyters</hi>) I shall then begin to miſdoubt many of My former <hi>foundations;</hi> (as for Bishop <hi>Davenant,</hi> he is none of thoſe, to whom I have appealed, or will ſubmit unto) but for the exception you take to <hi>Fathers,</hi> I take it to be a <hi>begging of the Queſtion;</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:178715:24"/>thoſe great diſcoveries of ſecrets, not knowne to former Ages, I shall call <hi>new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented fancies,</hi> untill particularly you shall prove the contrary; and for your <hi>Roman Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> it is no great wonder for them to ſeek shifts whereby to maintain <hi>Novelties,</hi> as well as the <hi>Puritans:</hi> As for <hi>Church-ambition,</hi> it doth not at all terminate, in ſeeking to be <hi>Pope;</hi> for, I take it to be no point of humility to endeavour to be <hi>independent of Kings,</hi> it being poſſible, that <hi>Papacy</hi> in a <hi>multitude</hi> may be as dangerous as in <hi>one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. As I am no <hi>Iudge</hi> over the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> ſo neither doe <hi>I</hi> cenſure them, for many things may be avowable upon <hi>neceſsity,</hi> which otherwaies are <hi>unlawfull;</hi> but know, once for all, that I eſteeme nothing the better becauſe it is done by ſuch a <hi>particular Church</hi> (though it were by the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which I avow moſt to reverence) but I eſteem that <hi>Church</hi> moſt, which comes neareſt to the <hi>purity of the primitive Doctrine and Diſcipline,</hi> as I believe this doth: Now concerning <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> I bad you prove that <hi>Presbyters</hi> with out a <hi>Bishop</hi> might lawfully <hi>ordaine,</hi> which yet I conceive you have not done; For, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. it is evident that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was at <hi>Timothies ordination;</hi> And albeit that all the <hi>ſeventy</hi> had their power immediately from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet it is as evident that our Saviour made a clear di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:178715:25"/>between the <hi>twelve Apoſtles</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> which is ſet down by three of the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> whereof Saint <hi>Marke</hi> calls it an <hi>ordination, Mark</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15. and S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſayes, <hi>And of them he choſe Twelve, &amp;c. Luke</hi> 6.13. onely S. <hi>Matthew</hi> doth but barely enumerate them by their names of diſtinction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.1 I ſuppoſe out of modeſty, himſelfe being one and the other two being none are more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: For <hi>the adminiſtration of Baptiſm,</hi> giving, but not granting what you ſay, it makes more for me then you: but I will not engage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on new Queſtions, not neceſſary for My pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. For My <hi>Oath,</hi> you doe well not to enter upon thoſe Queſtions you mention; and you had done as well to have omitted your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; but, out of diſcretion, I deſire you to collect your Anſwer out of the laſt Section; and for yur Argument, though the intention of My Oath be for the good of the <hi>Church col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective,</hi> therefore can I be diſpenſed withall by others than the <hi>repreſentative Body?</hi> certainly no more than the People can diſpence with Me for any <hi>Oaths</hi> I took in their favours, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the two <hi>Houſes of Parliament;</hi> as for future reformations, I will onely tell you that <hi>incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum non ſolvit Argumentum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. For the <hi>King</hi> my <hi>Fathers</hi> opinion, if it were not to ſpend time (as I believe) needleſly,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:178715:25"/>I could prove by living, and written teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, all, and more, then I have ſaid of Him, for His perſwaſion in theſe points which I now maintaine; and for your <hi>defenſive Warre,</hi> as I doe acknowledge it a great ſinne for any <hi>King</hi> to <hi>oppreſſe the Church,</hi> ſo I hold it abſolutely unlawful for <hi>Subjects</hi> (upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever) to make <hi>Warre</hi> (though <hi>defenſive</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>lawfull Soveraigne;</hi> againſt which no leſſe proofs will make Me yeild but <hi>Gods words;</hi> and let Me tell you, that upon ſuch, points as theſe, <hi>inſtances,</hi> as well as <hi>compariſons,</hi> are <hi>odious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Laſtly, you miſtake the <hi>Quaere</hi> in my firſt Paper to which this pretends to anſwer; for my Queſtion was not concerning <hi>force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (for I never doubted the lawfulneſſe of it) but <hi>force of Armes,</hi> to which, I conceive, it ſaies little or nothing, unleſſe (after My ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) you refer Me to the former Section; that which it doth, is meerly the <hi>asking of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> after a fine diſcourſe of the ſeveral wayes of <hi>perſwading</hi> rather than <hi>forcing</hi> of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: take notice, that there is none of theſe Sections but I could have enlarged to many more lines, ſome to whole pages; yet I choſe to be thus brief, knowing you will underſtand more by a word than others by along diſcourſe; truſting likewiſe to your ingenuity, that <hi>reaſon epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:178715:26"/>will weigh as much with you as if it were at large.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Iune</hi> 22. 1646.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For His Majeſtie. Concerning the Authority of the Fathers, and practiſe of the Church. <hi>Iuly</hi> 2. 1646.</head>
            <head type="sub">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Alex: Henderſon's</hi> third Paper.</head>
            <p>HAving in my former Papers preſſed the ſteps of your Majeſties Propoſitions, and finding by your Majeſties laſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Controverſies to be multiplied, (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) beyond your Majeſties intentions in the beginning; As concerning the <hi>Reforming Power:</hi> The <hi>Reformation of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> The <hi>difference betwixt a Bishop and a Presbyter;</hi> The <hi>warrants of Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> The <hi>Authority of Interpreting Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> The <hi>taking and keeping of Puplique
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:178715:26"/>Oathes;</hi> The <hi>forcing of Conſcience;</hi> and many other inferior, and ſubordinate Queſtions; which are Branches of thoſe maine Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: All which in a ſatisfactory manner to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in few words, I leave to more preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Spirits, who either ſee no knots of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, or can find a way rather to cut them aſſunder, than to unlooſe them; yet wil I not uſe any Tergiverſation; nor doe I decline to offer my humble Opinion with the Reaſons thereof, in there owne time concerning each of them; which in obedience to your Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I have begun to doe already. Onely Sir, by your Majeſties favourable permiſsion, for the greater expedition, and that the preſent velitations may be brought to ſome iſſue, I am bold to entreat that the Method may be a little altered, and I may have leave now to begin at a Principle, and that which should have been, <hi>inter Precognita;</hi> I meane the Rule: by which we are to proceed, &amp; to determine the preſent Controverſie of <hi>Church policy;</hi> without which we will be led into a labyrinth, and want a thred to wind us out againe. In your Majeſties firſt Paper, the <hi>univerſall cuſtome of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church,</hi> is conceived to be the Rule. In the ſecond Paper, Section the 5. The <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and the <hi>univerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Fathers,</hi> is made a convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when the <hi>Interpretation of Scripture</hi> is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:178715:27"/>doubtfull; In your third Paper, Sect. <hi>5. the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitive Church, and the univerſall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Fathers,</hi> is made Judge, and I known, that nothing is more ordinary in this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then to alleage <hi>Antiquity, perpetuall Succeſſion, univerſall conſent of the Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>univerſall practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> according to the Rule of <hi>Auguſtine, Quod univerſa tenet Eccleſia, nec à Conſilio inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed ſemper retentum eſt, non, niſi Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate Apoſtolicâ, traditum rectiſſime credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> There is in this Argument at the firſt view ſo much appearance of Reaſon, that it may much worke upon a modeſt mind; yet being well examined and rightly weighed, it will be found to be of no great weight; for beſides that the minor will never be made good in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of a <hi>Diocaeſan Bishop,</hi> having ſole power of Ordination, and Juriſdiction, there being a multitude of Fathers, who maintaine that <hi>Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop, and Persbyter are of one and the ſame Order;</hi> I shall humbly offer ſome few Conſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the major, becauſe it hath been an inlet to many dangerous Errors, and hath proved a mighty hinderance, and obſtruction to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, I deſire it may be conſidered, that whiles ſome make two Rules for defining Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; the word of God, and antiquity, which they will have to be received with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:178715:27"/>equall veneration) or, as the Papiſts call them, <hi>Canonicall Authority, and Catholicall Tradition;</hi> and others, make <hi>Scripture</hi> to be the onely <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Antiquity</hi> the authentick <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> the latter of the two ſeemes to me to be the greater errour: becauſe the firſt ſetteth up a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrallel,</hi> in the ſame degree with Scripture, but this would create a Superior, in a higher degree above Scripture: For the <hi>interpretation</hi> of the Fathers shall be the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and accounted the very Cauſe and Reaſon for which we conceive and believe ſuch a place of Scripture to have ſuch a ſence; and thus, Men shall have Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over our Faith, againſt 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. Our faith shall ſtand in the wiſedome of man, and not in the power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5. and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture shall be of private interpretation; For the Propheſie came not of old by the will of man, 2 <hi>Pet. 1.20, 22. Niſi homini Deus placuerit, Deus non erit, Homo jam Deo propitius eſſe debebit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That Scripture cannot be Authentical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interpreted but by Scripture, is manifeſt from Scripture: The Levites gave the ſenſe of the Law by no other means, but by Scripture it ſelf, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.8. Our Saviour for example to us, gave the true ſenſe of Scripture, againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravations of Satan, by comparing Scripture with Scripture, and not by alleaging and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies out of the Rabbins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. And the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:178715:28"/>Apoſtles, in their Epiſtles, uſed no other help, but the diligent comparing of Propheticall writings; like as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> will have us to compare the clearer light of the Apoſtles, with the more obſcure light of the Prophets. 2, <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. And when we betake our ſelves to the Fathers, we have need to take heed, that, with the Papiſts, we accuſe not the Scriptures of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, or imperfection.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Fathers themſelves (as they are cited by Proteſtant Writers) hold this Concluſion, that Scripture is not to be interpreted, but by Scripture it ſelfe: To this purpoſe, amongſt many other Teſtimonies, they bring the ſaying of <hi>Tertullian, Surge veritas, ipſa Scripturas tuas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretare, quam Conſuetudo non novit; nam ſi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcet, non eſſet:</hi> if it knew Scripture, it would be ashamed of it ſelfe, and ceaſe to be any more.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſome Errors have been received, and continued for a long time, in the Church: The <hi>Error of Free will beginning at</hi> Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>continued till the time of</hi> Reformation, <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was rejected by</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>as the</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right of Epiſcopacy <hi>was oppoſed by others. The Error about the</hi> Viſion of God, <hi>That</hi> the Souls of the Saints departed, ſee not the face of God, till the Judgement of the Great Day, <hi>was held by univerſall Conſent: the ſame may be ſaid of the error of the Millenaryes; and, which</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:178715:28"/>more nearly toucheth upon the preſent Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Ancients erred groſly about the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> which did begin to worke in the dayes of the Apoſtles. Many other Inſtances might be brought to prove the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall practiſe of the Church,</hi> as were not warranted by the Apoſtles; as in the Rites of <hi>Baptiſme and Prayer;</hi> and the forming up and drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the Articles of that Creed, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Symbolum Apoſtolicum;</hi> the obſervation of many <hi>Feaſts,</hi> and <hi>Faſts</hi> both Aniverſary, and Weekly.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That it is not a matter ſo incredible, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, as ſome would have it appeare to be, for the Primitive Church to have made a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den defection from the Apoſtolicall purity: The people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the short time of <hi>Moſes</hi> his abſence on the Mount, turned aſide quickly, and fell into horrible Idolatry, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. Soone after the death of <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> and the Elders that had ſeen the great works, which the Lord had done for <hi>Israel,</hi> there aroſe another Generation after them, which did evill in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. Soone after the bulding of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſetling of Religion by <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the worship of God was defiled with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry: when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had eſtablished the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he forſook the Law of the Lord, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.1. And the Apoſtle ſayes too the Galatians, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>I marvell that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:178715:29"/>you are ſo ſoone removed unto another Goſpel:</hi> why then shall we thinke it ſtrange, that in the matter of Diſcipline, there should be a ſudden defection, eſpecially it being begun in the time of the Apoſtles? I know it is a common Opinion, but I believe there be no ſtrong reaſons for it, that the Church which was neareſt the times of the Apoſtles was the moſt pure and perfect Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That it is impoſsible to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the univerſall Conſent and Practice of the Primitive Church: for many of the Fathers wrote nothing at all, many of their writings are perished, (it may be that both of theſe have diſſented from the reſt) many of the Writings which we have under their names are ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, &amp; counterfeit, eſpecially about Epiſcopacy, which was the foundation of Papall Primacy: The Rule of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> afore mentioned doth too much favour Traditions, and is not to be admitted, without cautions, and exceptions.</p>
            <p>Many the like Conſiderations may be added; but theſe may be ſufficient to prove, that the unanimous Conſent of the Fathers, and the univerſall practice of the Primitive Church, is no ſure ground of Authenticall interpretation of Scripture, I remember of a grave Divine in <hi>Scotland,</hi> much honoured by K. <hi>Iames</hi> of happy memory, who did often profeſſe that he did learne more of one Page of <hi>Iohn
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:178715:29"/>Calvin,</hi> then of a whole Treatiſe of <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> not can there be any good reaſon, (many there be againſt it) why the Ancients should be ſo farre preferred to the Moderne Doctors of the Reformed Churches, and the one in a manner Deified, and the other vilified: It is but a poor Reaſon that ſome give, <hi>Fama miratrix ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oris aevi,</hi> and is abundantly anſwered by the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt for Divine Providence. If your Majeſty be ſtill unſatisfied concerning the Rule, I know not to what purpoſe I should proceed or trouble your Majeſty any more.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 2. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Alex: Henderſon, <hi>Iuly</hi> 3. 1646.</head>
            <head type="sub">His MAIESTIES fourth Paper.</head>
            <p>TO shew a better way for clearing of the Scripture, I Shall very willingly follow the <hi>method</hi> you have begun in your third Paper; but I doe not conceive, that My laſt Paper multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies more Controverſies than My firſt gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for; having been ſo far from augmenting the Heads of our Diſputation, that I have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the anſwering many things, in both
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:178715:30"/>your Papers, expreſly to avoid raiſing of new, and needleſſe <hi>Queſtions;</hi> deſiring to have only ſo many debated, as are ſimply neceſſary to shew, whether, or not, <hi>I may with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience give way to the alteration of Church-Government in England;</hi> and indeed I like ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, to begin with the <hi>ſetling of the Rule,</hi> by which We are to proceed, and determine the preſent <hi>Controverſie;</hi> to which purpoſe (as I conceive) My third Paper shewes you an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way; for there, I offer you a <hi>Iudge</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, or deſire you to <hi>find out a better,</hi> which, to My judgement, you have not yet done, (though you have ſought to invalidate Mine) For, if you underſtand to have offered the <hi>Scripture</hi> though no Man shall pay more reverence, nor ſubmit more humbly to it, than My ſelf; yet We muſt find ſome rule to judge betwixt us, when you and I differ upon the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi> of the ſelfe-ſame Text, or it can never determine our Queſtions; as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I ſay you miſapply that of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. to <hi>Me</hi> (let others anſwer for themſelves) for I know not how I make <hi>other Men to have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over My Faith,</hi> when I make them onely <hi>ſerve</hi> to <hi>approve My reaſon;</hi> nor doe I conceive how, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5. can be applied to this purpoſe; For there Saint <hi>Paul</hi> onely shewes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Divine,</hi> and <hi>Humane Eloquence,</hi> making no mention of any kind of <hi>interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:178715:30"/>throughout the whole Chapter, as indeed Saint <hi>Peeter</hi> does, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. which I conceive makes for <hi>Me;</hi> for, ſince that no <hi>Propheſie of Scripture is of any private interpretation;</hi> Firſt, I inferre, that <hi>Scripture</hi> is to be <hi>Interpreted;</hi> for elſe, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would have omitted the word <hi>Private:</hi> Secondly, that at leaſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of many learned Divines is neceſſary, and ſo <hi>à fortiore,</hi> that of the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> ought to be an <hi>authentique Iudge,</hi> when Men differ: And is it a good Argument? becauſe (<hi>Mat.</hi> 4.4.7.10.) Scripture is beſt interpreted by it ſelfe, therefore that all other interpretations are unlawfull? certainly you cannot thinke: Thus having shewed you that We differ, about the <hi>meaning</hi> of the Scripture, and are like to do ſo; certainly there ought to be for this, as well as other things, a <hi>Rule,</hi> or a <hi>Iudge</hi> between us, to determine our differences, or, at leaſt, to make our probations, and Arguments Rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; therefore evading, for this time, to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your 6 <hi>Conſiderations</hi> (not I aſſure you for the difficulty of them, but the ſtarting of new Queſtions) I deſire you onely to shew Me a better, than what I have offered unto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 3. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:178715:31"/>
            <head>For Mr. Alex: Henderſon, A particular Anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Alex: Henderſons, Paper Iuly</hi> 2. 1646.</head>
            <head type="sub">His MAIESTIES fifth Paper.</head>
            <p>VNtill you shall find out a <hi>fitter way</hi> to decide our <hi>Difference</hi> in Opinion concerning <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture</hi> than the <hi>Conſent of the Fathers, an the univerſall Practice of the Primitive Church,</hi> I cannot but paſſe you My Judgment anent thoſe 6 <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> which you offered to invalidate thoſe Authorities, that I ſo much reverence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt you mention <hi>two Rules for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of Controverſies,</hi> and ſeeke a moſt old way to confute them, (as I think;) For you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage, that <hi>there is more attributed to them,</hi> then I believe you can prove, by the Conſent of moſt learned Men (there being no Queſtion, but there are alwaies ſome flattering Fooles that can commend nothing but with hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick expreſſions) and you know that <hi>ſuppoſito quolibet, ſequitur quidlibet;</hi> beſides doe you thinke, that albeit ſome ignorant Fellowes, should attribute more power to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> than is really due unto them, that thereby their juſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:178715:31"/>reverence, and authority is diminished? So I ſee no reaſon why I may not ſafely maintaine that the <hi>Interpretation of Fathers,</hi> is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>ſtrengthning</hi> to My Opinion, though Others should attribute the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their Faith unto it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As there is no Queſtion, but that <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is the farre <hi>beſt Interpreter</hi> of it ſelfe, ſo I ſee nothing in this, negatively proved, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any other, notwithſtanding your poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive affirmation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor in the next, for I hope you will not be the firſt to condemne your ſelfe, Me, and innumerable Others, who yet unblamably have not tyed themſelves to this Rule.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If in this you onely intend to prove, that <hi>Errors</hi> were alwaies <hi>breeding in the Church,</hi> I shall not deny it, yet that makes little (as I conceive) to your purpoſe; but if your meaning bee, to accuſe the <hi>univerſall Practice of the Church</hi> with <hi>Error,</hi> I muſt ſay it is a very bold undertaking; and, (if you cannot juſtifie your ſelfe by cleare places in Scripture) much to be blamed, wherein you muſt not alleage, that to be univerſally received, which was not, as I dare ſay, that the <hi>Controverſie about Free will,</hi> was never yet decided, by <hi>Oecumenicall,</hi> or <hi>Generall Councell;</hi> nor muſt you preſume to call that an <hi>Error,</hi> which really the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> maintained (as in <hi>Rites of Baptiſme,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:178715:32"/>Formes of Prayer, Obſervation of Feaſts; Faſts,</hi> &amp;c.) except you can prove it ſo by the Word of God; and it is not enough to ſay, that ſuch a thing was not warranted by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> but you muſt prove by their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> that ſuch a thing was <hi>unlawfull,</hi> or elſe the <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Church</hi> is warrant enough for Me to follow, and obey that Cuſtome, whatſoever it be, and thinke it good, and shall believe that the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> was made by them, (ſuch <hi>Reverence</hi> I beare to the <hi>Churches Tradition</hi>) untill other Authors be certainly found out.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I was taught that <hi>de poſſe ad eſſe</hi> was no good Argument; and indeed to Me it is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, that any <hi>cuſtome of the Catholique Church</hi> was erroneous, which was not contradicted, by <hi>orthodox,</hi> learned Men, in the times of their firſt Practice, as is eaſily perceived that all thoſe <hi>Defections</hi> were, (ſome of them may be juſtly called <hi>Rebellions</hi>) which you mention.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I deny it is <hi>impoſsible,</hi> (though I confeſſe it <hi>difficult</hi>) to come to the knowledge of the <hi>univerſall Conſent, and Practice of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> therefore I confeſſe a Man ought to be <hi>carefull</hi> how to believe things of this nature; wherefore I conceive this to be onely an Argument for <hi>Caution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Concluſion is, that albeit I never eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any <hi>Authority</hi> equall to the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> yet I doe thinke the <hi>unanimous Conſent of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:178715:32"/>Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>univerſall Practice of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, to be the beſt and moſt Authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Interpreters of Gods word,</hi> and conſequently the fitteſt Judges between Me, and you, when we differ, untill you shall find Me better: For example, I thinke you for the preſent, the beſt <hi>Preacher</hi> in <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> yet I believe you may erre, and poſſibly a better <hi>Preacher</hi> may come, but till then, muſt retaine My Opinion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. R.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 16. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:178715:33"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 16. Line 4. anothers, read another.</p>
            <p>Page 19. Line 2. nothing, read nothing is.</p>
            <p>Page 36. Line 16. I it, read it.</p>
            <p>Page 37. Line 18. with, read from.</p>
            <p>Page 38. Line 5. Preamble, read probable.</p>
            <p>Page 38. Line 18. your, read you.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
